Guide to the Stanford University Endowment Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University endowment records
1903-2004
SC0762
Augsburger, Robert, collector
12.5 Linear feet
Consists of original documents (in part, generated by Rodney Adams, Director of Finance 1976-1985), copies of documents (in part, from Stanford University Archives collections), and Augsburger's notes and completed research, including spreadsheets on endowment figures for 1903-2002. Other topics of note within the collection include the Uniform Management of Institutional Funds Act and the financial role of real estate (the Stanford Shopping Center and the research park).
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Robert Augsburger was Stanford's vice president for business and finance from 1971 to 1977 and a lecturer in management at the Graduate School of Business from 1971 until he retired in 1995. Prior to coming to Stanford, he was a Wall Street executive; he received a B.S. degree from Northwestern and a J. D. degree from Case Western Reserve University School of Law. He has also served with the Stanford Associates and the Stanford Historical Society.
Description of the Collection
Collection consists of original documents (in part, generated by Rodney Adams, Director of Finance 1976-1985), copies of documents (in part, from Stanford University Archives collections), and Augsburger's notes and completed research, including spreadsheets on endowment figures for 1903-2002. Other topics of note within the collection include the Uniform Management of Institutional Funds Act and the financial role of real estate (the Stanford Shopping Center and the research park).
Access Terms
Adams, Rodney.; Augsburger, Robert, collector; Universities and colleges--Finance.
Collection Contents
- Records, Accession ARCH-2004-187
  Adams refers to Rodney Adams, Director of Finance and Treasurer; he is represented in SC0068
  Transferred to Stanford Historic Photograph Collection:
  Photographs: results of Encina Hall attic fire circa 1972
  Removed from collection and discarded (duplicate of item in SC0486):
  Livingston and Blayney, Stanford University Land Use Policy/Plan, 1971
  - Ford Foundation Reports [note regarding location of] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Uniform Management of Institutional Funds [general] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Uniform Management of Institutional Funds Act – Statute current (Adams #1121) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Uniform Management of Institutional Funds Act – Statute (Adams #1122), -1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Uniform Management of Institutional Funds Act – reporting requirements (Adams #1123) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Uniform Management of Institutional Funds Act – Stanford implementation (Adams #1124) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Uniform Management of Institutional Funds Act – Stanford reports (Adams #1125) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous: Stanford Management Company (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous: Historical Data (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous: Documents (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Endowment payment (Adams' files), 1977-81 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Financing: Internal Endowment Payout: Background (Adams #1215) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Financing: Internal Endowment Payout: 5-yr income forecast (Adams #1217) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Financing: Internal Long-range Forecasts: Merged pool and EPF Payout: (Adams #1218) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Venture Distribution Policies (Adams #1382) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Internal Interest Rates on Advances of Funds (Adams #1219) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Extra copies of Parachini files [Victor M. Parachini, Capital Guardian Trust Co.], 1976-86 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Hoover Institution (Adams #1325) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Hoover Investment Issues (Adams #1326) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - DAPER Investment Pool (Adams #1321) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Other endowments: Harvard (Adams #1221) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Other endowments: Yale (Adams #1222) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Other endowments: California (Adams #1223) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Endowments generally, principally other institutions (Adams #1211) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Notebook: History of the Evolution of the Stanford Endowment 1903-2003. Archival Notes and Commentary. Robert R. Augsburger, 2004 Sep (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Admin: Department: SUIMO (209 Hamilton, PA): general (Adams #6361) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Real Estate, general (1 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Real Estate, general (2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Real Estate: Gen/Policy: general correspondence (Adams #7111) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Real Estate: Tax advantage financing – sale-leasebacks (Adams #7123) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Real Estate: Tax and legal issues (Adams #7124) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Real Estate: Gen/Policy: Leasing – land lease guidelines (Adams #7131) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Real Estate: Gen/Policy: Leasing – Leasing and lease extension analysis (Adams #7133) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Real Estate: Stanford Shopping Center (SSC) – general (Adams #7241) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Real Estate: Stanford Shopping Center (SSC) – renovation (Adams #7242) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Real Estate: Stanford Shopping Center (SSC) – final phases (Adams #7243) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Real Estate: Stanford Shopping Center (SSC) – theaters (Adams #7244) (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Real Estate: Alpine Chalet – audit reports (Adams #7251) (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Real Estate: Alpine Chalet - general (Adams #7252) (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Real Estate: Out Properties – report to Trustees (Adams #7212) (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Option Writing – research, proposals and related materials (Adams #3251), 1973-81 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Option Writing – research, proposals and related materials (Adams #3251), 1973-81 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - [Risk] Arbitrage Background (Adams #3211) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Investment Management Cost Allocation (Adams #3152) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - ACCOUNT/TAX: Taxation: Legislation - Unrelated Business Income (Adams # 5424) (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - ACCOUNT/TAX: Endowment: General/Policy – general (Adams #5211) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Insurance and Risk Management Reports, 1980-84 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Advisory Task Force on Retirement Plan Alternatives. Final Report, May 1977 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Stanford Business School Trust Fund (Adams #1451) (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Archival Materials (copies of documents with Augsburger's notes & analysis), 1903-1975 (Box 5)
  - Archival Materials (copies of documents with Augsburger's notes & analysis), 1976-1997 (Box 6)
  - Archival Materials (copies of documents with Augsburger's notes & analysis), 1998-2002 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Archival Materials (copies of documents with Augsburger's notes & analysis), 1998-2002 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Archival Materials (copies of documents with Augsburger's notes & analysis), 1998-2002 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Annual Reports, 1920s (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Annual Reports, 1930s (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Annual Reports, 1940s (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Annual Reports, 1950s (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Annual Reports, 1960s (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Annual Reports, 1970s (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1981-1990 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Annual Reports, 1991-2000 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Annual Reports, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Annual Reports, extra copies (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Quarterly Financial Reports, 1975-1988 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Stanford University Investment Performance Summary As of December 31, 1976 (Becker Securities Corporation) (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Facilities Plan and Capital Funding Forecast 1975 to 1980 (March 1975) (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Facilities Plan and Capital Funding Forecast 1976 to 1981 (April 1976) (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Facilities Plan and Capital Funding Forecast 1977 to 1982 (May 1977) (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - "Constrained Maximization of a University Preference Function" by William F. Massy and David S. P. Hopkins. Academic Planning Office, Feb. 1975 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - "Long-run Financial Equilibrium Calculations for Stanford's Operating Budget," by William F. Massy and David S. P. Hopkins. Academic Planning Office, Sept. 1974 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - "A Dynamic Equilibrium Model for University Budgeting," by William F. Massy, Academic Planning Office, Oct. 1974 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - "A Model for Planning the Transition to Equilibrium of a University Budget," by David S. P. Hopkins and William F. Massy, Academic Planning Office, Dec. 1974 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - "Planning Models for Top Administrators in Colleges and Universities," by William F. Massy, Academic Planning Office, Jan. 1974 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - "Stanford University Energy Management and Conservation Program; a report to the Board of Trustees", April 1977 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Final Report Palo Alto-Menlo Park Area Transportation Project by the PAMTRANS Study Group, James V. Jucker, Director, Nov. 1975 (Box 8, Folder 17)
- Records, Accession ARCH-2004-246
  - Augsburger, Robert, "Evolution of an Endowment--100 Years of Trusteeship", 2003 May (Box 1)
  - Swenson, David, Pioneering Portfolio Management (New York: The Free Press), 2000 (Box 1)
  - National Association of College and University Business Officers (NACUBO), Endowment Study, 2002; 1.1; 9 computer file(s) (PDF) (Box 1)
  - Dengler, Herb, leading tour of local land trust staff at Jasper Ridge, 1986 Apr 11; 1.2; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 1)
  - Steer, Stanley on Al Mauspeaker; John Packar, 2001 May 6; Apr 24; 1.3; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 1)
  - Parachini, Vic, 2001 May 30; 1.4; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 1)
  - Dennis, Reid, 2003 Mar 12; 1.5; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 1)
  - Dennis, Reid, 2003 Mar 14; 1.6; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 1)
  - Dengler, Herb, leading tour of local land trust staff at Jasper Ridge, 1.7; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 1)
- Records, Accession ARCH-2005-192
  Except for folder 1, this accession consists of printed spreadsheets from Augsburger's research on the Stanford endowment.
  - Ford Foundation Endowment Papers ["Investment Management for Endowed Institutions," 2001, and "Measuring Investment Results by the Unit Method"] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Original Stanford Endowment (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Endowment income (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Market Value – Endowment Assets, 1903-2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Endowment Book to Market, 1903-2002 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Limited Partnerships, 1980-2002 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Real Estate (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Excel files for above spreadsheets, 15 computer file(s) (Box 1, Folder 8)